<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the army of the Commonwealth of England, to the people of Scotland. Signed in the name, and by the appointment of his Excellency the Lord General Cromwel and his councel of officers. Jo: Rushworth secr'</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E608_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865137</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865137</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165692</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165692)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E608[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the army of the Commonwealth of England, to the people of Scotland. Signed in the name, and by the appointment of his Excellency the Lord General Cromwel and his councel of officers. Jo: Rushworth secr'</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Husband and John Field, printers to the Parliament of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>July 23. 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165692:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE ARMY OF THE Commonwealth OF <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> To the People of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>SIgned in the Name, and by the Appointment of His Excellency the Lord General <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> and His Councel of Officers.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Jo: RUSHWORTH Secr.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Huſband</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to the Parliament of <hi>England. July</hi> 23. 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:165692:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165692:2"/>
            <head>To the People of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas the Army under my Conduct, by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> is to advance into <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon the grounds, and for the ends expreſſed in their Declaration of <hi>Iune</hi> 26. 1650. And conſidering the ſeveral ways and practiſes of ſome in that Kingdom, whoſe deſign it hath been, and ſtill is, by all maner of groundleſs and unjuſt Reproaches, and moſt falſe Slanders, to make the Army odious, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us unto the people, as ſuch that are to be abhorred of all pious, peaceable and ſober Spirits, and to be rather Monſters then Men.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165692:3"/>
            <p>VVe think fit therefore, for the clearing of our ſelves, to reminde you of our former deportment and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior, when about two years ſince we entred into the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and then carryed in by the Hand of Divine Providence, and through the earneſt Invitation of thoſe now in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Authority and Power with you, VVhat injury or wrong did we then do, either to the perſons, Houſes or Goods of any? <hi>Whoſe Ox have we ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken?</hi> Did we ſeek any thing for our ſelves? Did we other then preſerve the beſt affected from; their and our moſt deſperate enemies? And having eſtabliſhed our Inviters in their power without doing the leaſt violence to any, we returned to our own Nation.</p>
            <p>And conſidering this, we have cauſe to hope, That thoſe former carriages
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165692:3"/>of ours are not ſo ſoon forgotten; and that the preſent Miſreports of what our dealings will be, ſhall not diſturb, nor affright the people from their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and dwellings.</p>
            <p>And for ſatisfaction of all thoſe that are Lovers of Religion, Peace and Publique Liberty, and being deſirous to put a difference between the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and the Guilty; VVe do hereby Declare, in the Integrity of our hearts, That as to the Gentry and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of the Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe Habitations are in thoſe places, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Army by the providence of God may come, <hi>As we know full well they are not the Perſons, who by their Councels and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings have laid the certain foundation of a ſecond unrighteous and unjuſt Invasion of</hi> England, <hi>by clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with, and entertaining of Him, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165692:4"/>ſtirs up, and labors to engage many For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes to invade the</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>and hath exerciſed actual: hoſtility againſt the Nation, by deſtroying the People, and Commiſsiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pirats to kill our Men, and to rob, ſpoil, and take away our Ships and Goods by Sea, to the ruine of</hi> England, <hi>ſo much as in Him lies; Nor of thoſe who have refuſed ſo much as a Treaty with the</hi> Commonwealth <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>wherein onely a juſt and equal ſatisfaction for paſt Injuries was aimed at, and a ſecurity for a firm Peace between the two Nations deſired: Which denial, and other practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hath put us upon this unavoidable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of entring into</hi> Scotland, <hi>unleſs we would have ſtood ſtill, and Jeen, not onely the deſtruction of the godly and well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, but alſo of the very Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Holineſs in both Nations:</hi> So
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165692:4"/>we ſhall not (the Lord continuing his goodneſs and preſence to us) offer the leaſt violence and injury to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, goods or poſſeſsions of any of them, but ſtrive and labor to our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to prevent all diſorders that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen from an Army, and to give all ſpeedy Redreſs and Satisfaction that poſsibly may be, when any juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of Miscarriage ſhall be made.</p>
            <p>And upon the Confidence of theſe our ſincere and honeſt intentions (which we hope our good and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God will enable us to perform;) VVe do hereby INVITE all ſuch perſons to ſtay and abide in their own Houſes and Habitations, where they may and ſhall enjoy what they have in peace; and not to ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be miſ-led by the craft and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165692:5"/>ſubtilty of any, into that which muſt needs prove their inevitable Loſs and Ruine, and a great hazard to their Countrey.</p>
            <p>Howſoever, we have done this, as our Duty to God, and for ſatisfaction to all good men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed in the Name, and by the Appointment of His Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency the Lord General</hi> Cromwel, <hi>and His Councel of Officers,</hi> Joh: Rushworth <hi>Secretary.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
